Fulton County Typographical Union, No. 268; Records apap018
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Fulton County Typographical Union No. 268 Records
1894-1973
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Typographical Union No. 268
apap018
1.25 cubic ft.
The Fulton County Typographical Union No. 268 records document the workings of this union, primarily, in the form of minutes, from 1894-1973.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, Fulton County Typographical Union, No. 268, CWA. The records were subsequently microfilmed as part of the Harry Van Arsdale, Jr., Labor History Project.
Administrative History
In January of 1894, printers of Fulton County, New York, met to consider the formation of a typographical union. On March 19 of that year, the Fulton County Typographical Union, No. 268, was chartered by the International Typographical Union (ITU) according to Fulton County Typographical Union, No. 268, Minutes, 1894. Although the union had jurisdiction over all of Fulton County, the printers were generally employed in composing rooms in Gloversville and Johnstown, the county's twin cities.
In 1933, in the middle of the depression, the printers of Fulton County endured some of their most difficult contract negotiations. The local newspaper publishers were losing advertisement because of the economic conditions in the county and the nation as a whole, so they demanded that the printers take wage cuts. After a few months of discussion and the introduction of strikebreakers by the American Newspaper Publishers Association, the union finally acceded to the publishers' demands according to Fulton County Typographical Union, No. 268, Minutes, 1933.
The Fulton County Typographical Union, No. 268, has always been small. The union never had more than approximately 50 members, and now it has substantially less than half that number. With the difficulties of running a small union and the pressure to consolidate, the Fulton County Typographical Union might some day merge with the Albany Typographical Union No. 4.
Scope and Contents
The records of the Fulton County Typographical Union, No. 268, are remarkable for containing a complete set of minutes (1894-1963). included in the minutes are financial statements of the union, reports of delegates to conventions, and occasional correspondence. All the contracts of the union have not survived, but there is a good selection of them for the years 1901 to 1963. There are, however, gaps of many years in these contracts, and the contracts are especially voluminous in the first twelve years of the twentieth century. A couple of other items are included in this collection--a constitution and a scale report--but they are not as important as are the other types of material.
These records provide insight into the workings of a small union over almost a century of development. The fluctuations of the workforce and the introduction of new technologies play a role in the progress of this union, as do the necessary sacrifices of a small union in an often depressed economy. In recent years, Fulton County has had the highest unemployment in New York State.
For related records, see the records of the Albany Typographical Union No. 4, 1850-55, 1869, 1874-1988; Graphic Communications International Union, Local 259-M, 1941, 1946-88; and the records of the Empire Typographical and Mailer Conference, 1919-20, 1929-75, 1983, 1985-88, 1990. Other available records related to Fulton County include the records of the Glove Cities Area Joint Board, ACTWU, 1933-89; and occasional items in the records of the Graphic Communications International Union, Local 259-M. For additional labor collections in the Department, see the online Labor subject guide.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1 - Minutes, 1894-1963, Undated
Series 2 - Subject Files, 1901-1910, 1912, 1918, 1925, 1930, 1953-1954, 1957, 1959, 1961, 1963, Undated
Labor; Labor union locals--United States; New York (State); Fulton County (N.Y.); Administrative records; Minutes; Contracts; Fulton County Typographical Union, No. 268 Records
- Minutes, 1894-1963; 1
  - Minutes, 1894-1901 (Box 1 (1-Minutes), Folder 1)
  - Minutes, 1902-1909 (Box 1 (1-Minutes), Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 1910-1915 (Box 1 (1-Minutes), Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 1916-1919 (Box 1 (1-Minutes), Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 1920-1923 (Box 1 (1-Minutes), Folder 5)
  - Minutes, 1924-1927 (Box 1 (1-Minutes), Folder 6)
  - Minutes, 1928-1930 (Box 1 (1-Minutes), Folder 7)
  - Minutes, 1930-1934 (Box 1 (1-Minutes), Folder 8)
  - Minutes, 1935-1940 (Box 1 (1-Minutes), Folder 9)
  - Minutes, 1941-1945 (Box 1 (1-Minutes), Folder 10)
  - Minutes, 1946-1951 (Box 1 (1-Minutes), Folder 11)
  - Minutes, 1952-1955 (Box 1 (1-Minutes), Folder 12)
  - Minutes, 1956-1959 (Box 1 (1-Minutes), Folder 13)
  - Minutes, 1960-1963 (Box 1 (1-Minutes), Folder 14)
- Subject Files, 1901-1912; 1918; 1925; 1930; 1953-1963; 2
  - Constitution and Rules of Order, 1954 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 1)
  - Contracts, Sample, 1930 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 2)
  - Contracts, American Fancier, 1901 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 3)
  - Contracts, A. E. Blanck, 1901-1903 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 4)
  - Contracts, Byron & Scovic, 1918 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 5)
  - Contracts, Collins & Combes Publishing Company, 1902-1905; 1908 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 6)
  - Contracts, William B. Collins Company, 1901; 1909; 1925; 1930; 1953-1963 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 7)
  - Contracts, James S. Comrie, 1906; 1908 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 8)
  - Contracts, Daily Leader, 1905-1907 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 9)
  - Contracts, Fulton County Democrat, 1912 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 10)
  - Contracts, John B. Judson, 1901-1903; 1905-1907; 1909-1910; 1925 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 11)
  - Contracts, Labor News Publishing Company, 1902 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 12)
  - Contracts, Merwin Printing Company, 1925 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 13)
  - Contracts, Morning Herald Printing Company, 1902-1903; 1905-1908; 1925 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 14)
  - Contracts, H. Ross [Owner of the Gloversville Standard and the Morning Herald], 1901 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 15)
  - Contracts, Charles M. Smith, 1901-1903 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 16)
  - Contracts, James W. Snyder, 1902; 1905-1906; 1908-1909 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 17)
  - History of Fulton County Typographical Union by E. L. Wert, (MISSING), Aug., 1987 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 18)
  - Scale Report, 1904 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 19)